例如，我们现在要考虑一个在三维空间中移动的物体
We are now going to consider an object which moves in three-dimensional space, for instance
这架飞机可能是一个飞行机器人，它可能是一个水下机器人。
this airplane but it could be a flying robot, it could be an underwater robot.
我想描述它在世界上的位置。
I want to describe its position within the world.
我们将使用与二维相同的过程。
And we are going to use the same process that we did for two dimensions.
我们将介绍一个参考坐标系。
We’re going to introduce a reference coordinate frame.
现在，对于三维情况，这是一个三维坐标系。
Now, for the three-dimensional case, this is a three-dimensional coordinate frame.
它有一个x轴，一个y轴和一个z轴。
It’s got an x-axis, a y-axis and a z-axis.
并且，我将把它放在世界上任意的地方，那将是
And, I’m going to put it at an arbitrary place in the world and that is going to be
我们的参考坐标系。
our reference coordinate frame.
在三个维度中，我们使用了一个看起来像这样的坐标框架，并且有一个
In three dimensions, we used a coordinate frame that looks like this and there are a
与我们在上一讲中看到的2D坐标框架有许多相似之处。
lot of similarities to the 2D coordinate frame we looked at in the last lecture.
有三个轴。
There are three axes.
它们是x，y和z，它们相互成90度角相交。
They are x, y and z and they meet at angles of 90 degrees to each other.
它们都相交的点被称为原点。
The point where they all intersect is referred to as the origin.
因此，这三个轴一起形成我们称之为三维坐标系。
So, these three axes together form what we call a three-dimensional coordinate frame.
现在让我们介绍一个观点，我们想要描述一下这一点
Let’s introduce a point now and we want to describe the point with respect to the
3D坐标框架。
3D coordinate frame.
我们通过将一条线向下放到XY平面并测量位移A来做到这一点
We do this by dropping a line down to the XY plane and measuring the displacement A
沿x轴，沿y轴的位移B和沿着x轴的位移C.
along the x-axis, the displacement B along the y-axis and the displacement C along the
z轴。
z-axis.
所以，我们可以用三个数字来表示这一点。
So, we can represent the point by three numbers.
我们称之为元组，一个三元组，这基本上是一组三个数字，即数字
We call this a tuple, a 3-tuple, and that’s basically a group of three numbers, the numbers
A，B和C，它们是该点的坐标。
A, B and C and they are the coordinates of the point.
因此，我们可以认为一个点是n维空间中的一个位置。
So, we can consider a point is a location in an n-dimensional space.
一位数学家会把它写成P属于实数的集合
A mathematician would write that as P belonging to the set of real numbers to the power of
ñ。
n.
在这种特殊情况下，n等于3。
And in this particular case, n is equal to three.
在最一般意义上，我们可以将坐标表示为n的组或元组
In the most general sense, we can represent the coordinate as a group or a tuple of n
数字。
numbers.
同样，在这种情况下，n等于3，因此它用包括的坐标表示一个点
Again, in this case, n equals three, so it represents a point by a coordinate which comprises
三个数字。
three numbers.
我们可以用三个组件来描述一个向量：一个与之平行的组件A.
We can describe a vector in terms of three components: a component A parallel to the
x轴，平行于y轴的分量B和平行于z轴的分量C.
x-axis, component B parallel to the y-axis, and a component C parallel to the z-axis.
并且，我们使用小写符号p和列向量表示向量P.
And, we represent the vector P using the lower case symbol p and a column vector.
这是一堆数字一个在另一个之上：距离A，距离B和
That’s a stack of numbers one above the other: the distance A, the distance B and
距离C.矢量是n维矢量空间的元素。
the distance C. A vector is an element of an n-dimensional vector space.
一位数学家会说小写p属于一组实数
A mathematician would say that lower case p belongs to the set of real numbers to the
的力量
power of n.
同样，在这种情况下，n等于3。
Again, in this case, n equals 3.
我们还可以通过n个元素列向量表示向量。
We can also represent a vector by an n element column vector.
这是n个数字叠加在另一个之上。
That’s n numbers stacked one above the other.
我们可以将矢量视为相对位移。
We can consider a vector as a relative displacement.
这就是我们从原点，我们的参考点到直线点p的方式。
That’s how we get from the origin, our reference point, to the point p in a straight line.
我们要考虑的所有向量都是从原点开始的，所以我们参考这些向量
All the vectors that we’re going to consider start at the origin, so we refer to these
作为绑定向量。
as bound vectors.
他们有一个特定的起点。
They have a particular starting point.
并且，这意味着此处显示的红色矢量与此处显示的此矢量不同
And, that means that the vector shown here in red is different to this vector shown here
即使它在空间中具有相同的长度和相同的方向。
even though it has got the same length and the same orientation in space.
我们可以描述向量的另一种方式是根据一组正交单位向量。
Another way we can describe vectors is in terms of a set of orthogonal unit vectors.
让我们介绍单位向量，x-hat，y-hat和z-hat。
Let’s introduce the unit vectors, x-hat, y-hat and z-hat.
现在，这些向量中的每一个都具有一个长度，并且它们与坐标平行
Now, each of these vectors has got a length of one and they are parallel to the coordinate
轴，x，y和z。
axes, x, y and z.
现在，我们可以用单位向量表示我们的向量小写p。
Now, we can represent our vector lower case p in terms of the unit vectors.
时间为x-hat，B次为y-hat，加上C次为z-hat。
A time x-hat, B times y-hat, plus C times z-hat.
有一些相似之处，但点和向量之间存在一些重要的差异。
There are some similarities, but some important differences between points and vectors.
点定义一个位置。
Points define a location.
这是不可能的。
It’s not possible.
添加或乘以点没有任何意义。
It doesn’t make any sense to add or multiply points.
向量不定义位置。
Vectors do not define location.
它们指定了如何从一个位置到另一个位置或从一个点到另一个点。
They specify how to get from one location to another or from one point to another.
现在，我们可以添加和减去向量，这是完全有意义的，我们可以乘以a
Now, we can add and subtract vectors, that makes perfect sense and we can multiply a
矢量由标量。
vector by a scalar.
我们可以在保持方向的同时使矢量更长或更短。
We can make the vector longer or shorter while maintaining its direction.
两点之间的差异是矢量。
The difference between two points is a vector.
并且一个点可以被定义为相对于另一个点的向量，并且该点是
And a point can be defined as a vector with respect to another point and that point is
通常是坐标系的原点。
typically the origin of the coordinate frame.
点和向量都由一组n个实数表示。
Points and vectors are both represented by a group of n real numbers.
在我们的例子中，N是三，因为我们谈论的是三维空间。
N, in our case, is three because we’re talking about three-dimensional space.
点通常表示为行向量，括号内的数字列表，
A point is typically represented as a row vector, a list of numbers inside parenthesis,
而矢量通常表示为上面的n个数字的堆栈
whereas a vector is typically represented as a stack of the n numbers one above the
其他，通常在方括号中。
other and typically in square brackets.
现在，我可以描述飞机相对于该坐标系的位置。
Now, I can describe the position of the airplane with respect to this coordinate system.
我需要在飞机上定义一个参考点。
I need to define a reference point on the airplane.
我需要描述一个特定的位置。
I need to describe one particular location.
那么，让我们说一下飞机机头的尖端。
So, let’s say the tip of the airplane’s nose.
现在，我可以测量那个距离。
Now, I can measure that distance.
粗略地说，我会说它在X方向上大约35厘米，它可能是某种东西
Roughly, I’d say it’s about 35 centimetres in the X direction and it might be something
就像在Y方向上的18厘米，它的长度相差13厘米
like 18 centimetres in the Y direction and it’s something like 13 centimetres in the
Z方向。
Z direction.
所以，我可以通过那些来描述这个特定点在三维世界中的位置
So, I can describe the position of this particular point in the 3-dimensional world by those
三个数值坐标。
three numerical coordinates.